### LUISE MALMACEDA (She/Her)

#### **PROFILE**

Luise Malmaceda (Brazil, 1988) is a Ph.D. student in Latin American and Iberian Cultures at Columbia University. She holds a B.A. in Visual Arts from the Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul and a M.A. in Aesthetics and Art History from the Universidade de São Paulo. Her research interests include 20th century avant-garde art, music, cinema and poetry, with emphasis on underground and countercultural movements of the 1960s; experimental and conceptual practices in visual arts and their challenges of institutionalization; and Brazilian cultural resistance to the civilmilitary dictatorship (1964-1985).

She worked as an associate curator at Instituto Tomie Ohtake (São Paulo) from 2016 to 2020, creating curatorial projects, researching and writing for exhibitions and catalogues, and lecturing courses on modern and contemporary art history. She was also a jury member of the award EDP nas Artes (2018), editor of Harper's Bazaar Art magazine (2015), and art educator and researcher at Fundação Vera Chaves Barcellos (2012) and Fundação Iberê Camargo (2010).

#### CONTACT

lu.malmaceda@gmail.com or lbm2138@columbia.edu

414W 120th St, #307 New York - NY.

#### **EDUCATION**

# PhD in Latin American and Iberian Cultures 2020 - current

Columbia University (LAIC-CU)

# Master of Arts in Aesthetics and Art History 2015 – 2018

University of São Paulo (PGEHA - USP) Advisor: Cristina Freire, Ph.D. Fellowship from Capes

### Member of the Study Group in Conceptual Art and Conceptualism in Museums at the University of São Paulo (GEACC) 2015 - 2019

Coordinated by Cristina Freire, professor and curator of MAC-USP - Museum of Contemporary Art of the University of São Paulo

## Graduate (Latu-sensu) in Art History 2014 – 2016

Armando Álvares Penteado Foundation (FAAP)

# Exchange Program at University of Porto Portugal, 2011

Department of Visual Arts at University of Porto (FBAUP), Portugal

### Bachelor in Visual Arts 2008 – 2013

Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul (UFRGS)

#### Languages

Portuguese, Spanish, English

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Associate curator at Instituto Tomie Ohtake | 2016 - 2020

- Conceiving curatorial projects;
- Assistant of the chief curator, Paulo Miyada, and other guest curators;
- Research work for all exhibitions, producing content for catalogs, audioguides, press releases and other promotional materials;
- Writing of curatorial, institutional and informative statements for exhibitions;
- Spokesperson of the institute providing statements, briefings and interviews for newspapers and television;
- Conducting guided tours for groups of partners and specialists;
- Lecturing and courses on topics addressed in exhibitions.

### Lecturer at the Escola Espaço do Olhar - Instituto Tomie Ohtake | 2017 - current

Courses "An Immersion into Art History: from 1950 to 1980" and "Art and Brazilian Culture: 1950s, 60s and 70s".

#### **Cultural Awards Jury Member**

Bravo! de Cultura, 2017 6th EDP nas Artes, 2018 72th Salão de Abril, 2021

## Editor of Harper's Bazaar Art Brazil magazine 2015

- Content Editor of Issues 4 and 5 of the magazine;
- Elaboration of guidelines;
- Text writing;
- Conducting interviews.

### Undergraduate Scientific Initiation Researcher - CNPq Scholarship - Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul 2012 - 2013

Researcher on the problems of conservation of new media art under the guidence of Ana Maria Albani de Carvalho, Phd.

## Researcher at Fundação Vera Chaves Barcellos 2012

- Research and cataloging of the collection of the institution;
- Assistance for curators;

# **Educator at Fundação Iberê Camargo 2010**

- Guided visits in exhibitions of modern and contemporary art;
- Research for the design of teaching materials;
- Training courses for teachers.

#### **Prizes**

Jabuti Award 2020 in the category Arts/Essays for the book "AI-5 50 anos: ainda não terminou de acabar".

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

## Catalogues published by Instituto Tomie Ohtake:

# AI-5 50 ANOS – Ainda não terminou de acabar, 2019

Contributed as researcher, writer, as well as the curator responsible for the theater material related to the exhibition. The publication was nominated one of the best art books of 2019 by The New York Times, and was also the winner of the Jabuti Award in the category Arts/Essays in 2020.

https://www.nytimes.com/2019/12/05 /arts/design/best-art-books-2019.html

### Aprendendo com Miguel Bakun: Subtropical, 2019

Curator of the exhibition alongside Paulo Miyada.

### Alucinações parciais: Exposiçãoescola com obras-primas modernas do Brasil e do Centre Pompidou, 2018

Writes about artists Ismael Nery and Vicente do Rego Monteiro.

### Quando nós estamos? O Tempo e o Prêmio EDP nas Artes. São Paulo: Instituto Tomie Ohtake, 2018

Curator of the exhibition, alongside Paulo Miyada, Priscyla Gomes and Theo Monteiro.

# Osso: exposição-apelo ao amplo direito de defesa de Rafael Braga, 2017

Writes a critical essay about the public program of the exhibition.

#### Other catalogues:

#### O que não é performance?, 2016

Published by Centro Universitário Maria Antônia e Teatro da Universidade de São Paulo.

Avaiable: https://pt.scribd.com/docume nt/333539046/O-que-nao-e-performance

# A Medida do Gesto: Um panorama do acervo do MACRS, 2012

Published by Museu de Arte Contemporânea do Rio Grande do Sul.

#### Articles in books:

# Terra Brasilis: arte brasileira no acervo conceitual do MAC USP.

Organized by Cristina Freire and published by MAC-USP.

Avaiable: http://www.livrosabertos.sibi. usp.br/portaldelivrosUSP/catalog/book/ 356

### Escrita da História e (re)construção das memórias: arte e arquivos em debate, 2017

Organized by Cristina Freire. São Paulo: MAC-USP/Annablume, 2017.

#### Academic articles:

### O Projeto Variable Media e a extroversão das práticas de conservação da arte das novas mídias, 2015

Jornada de Pesquisa em Arte PPG IA-UNESP - Edição Internacional, 2015, São Paulo.

# Problemáticas de acervo das novas mídias na arte contemporânea, 2014

13° Encontro Internacional de Arte e Tecnologia (#13.ART): arte, política e singularidade, 2014, Brasília.

For more publications, please access: http://lattes.cnpq.br/2317708946568271